(upbeat music)
- Hello English learners,
welcome back to English Pod.
My name is Marco.
- And I'm Erica.
- And today we're gonna be bringing you the
second part of our job interview series.
- That's right, so this
is an advanced lesson.
And we're gonna be talking about
educational background and experience.
- Right, so in the first part, we
saw preparing for a job interview.
Now we are at the job interview
and we're just gonna be talking about
your educational background
and your job experience.
- That's right, and the
language we're gonna
learn is gonna focus
mostly on these two areas.
- Okay, perfect.
So let's take a look at
some of the difficult words
before we listen to the
dialogue in vocabulary preview.
- Very vocabulary preview.
- All right, so we're gonna talk about
a few common words that
have to do with education.
Now the first words, I
think we might know
this one, but there's
a little trick to it.
So the first one is major.
- Major.
So, yeah, I guess everyone
knows what a major is, right?
- Yeah, it's the main subject
that you study in university.
- Right, so you can study business
as a major or-- - History, yeah.
- So, but you can also
use it as a verb, right?
- That's right, I majored in history.
- Majored in.
So, usually it's followed
by the preposition in.
- Yes, oh, as, in fact, when used
as a verb, I majored in science.
- I majored in business.
- Yes.
- Okay, so you can say my
major is business administration
or history, or you can
say I majored in business.
- Yeah, and the same
pattern applies to minor.
- Okay, so minor,
this is really interesting
because this is more common in
English speaking countries, right?
- That's right.
- So what exactly is a minor?
- Well, just like your
major, but smaller, okay.
So, if you major in
history, maybe 60% of your
classes are in history
and you minor in French,
maybe 30 or 40% of
your classes are in French.
- So, basically, you can have
two subjects in your degree.
You can have a major in
business with a minor in art.
- Yes.
- Okay, that's interesting.
- Mm-hmm.
- All right, and another two
simple words, a bachelor's degree.
- Bachelor's degree, okay.
- A bachelor's degree is what you get
after going to university for four years.
- Okay, so a bachelor's degree,
after four years, you get that.
- Yeah, after that, you
get a master's degree.
- Right.
- So that's another two years
after your bachelor's degree.
- Okay, and I guess a master's is
more focused on an area, right?
- Yes, more specialized.
- More specialized.
- And then the highest
degree you can get is a PhD.
- Exactly.
- Which is a philosophy doctor, right?
But you're not actually
getting a degree of philosophy.
- No, it could be in
international relations.
- Okay, but this is really hard to get.
You have to go to school for
another five or six years, right?
- Yeah.
- And it's a lot of research
and not many people have it.
- Yeah.
Anyway, some simple
words, but you know what?
It's quite unique to the
English-speaking world
this system, so we thought
we'd bring it to you now.
- Right, perfect.
So now let's listen to this
guy who is at an interview,
and he's going to be talking about
his education and work experience.
(upbeat music)
- Thanks for coming in today.
Did you have any trouble finding us?
Please take a seat.
- Thank you.
Well, let's get started.
Tell me a bit about your
educational background.
- Sure, well, I graduated
with honors from Chesterton
University, with a major
in business administration,
with a specialization in information
management, and I'm honored in psychology.
I chose this course of
study for two reasons.
I wanted to gain some
practical, marketable skills,
which the information
management track provided,
and I also feel that the
interpersonal skills are essential
for professional success
hence the minor in psychology.
- Interesting, and your
postgraduate studies?
- Well, I am really
passionate about consumer
behavior, so I pursued
a master's in that area.
I also strive to keep my
professional skills current,
so I continuously attend
seminars and conferences
related to management
and customer service.
Very good.
Now, tell me a little bit
about your work experience.
I see here that you
previously worked at Oracle.
- Yeah, I worked as their
customer support manager,
which brought me a breadth of experience
in both client care and process management.
I supervised and coordinated
the customer support team
as well as implemented new strategies
to achieve better customer satisfaction.
- Ugh, interesting.
- Yes, in this position, I was
able to make some pretty
significant contributions to the
overall success of the company.
With the different initiatives
that we implemented,
we lowered our turn rate to about 5%,
which had a direct impact on revenue.
(upbeat music)
- Well, those are some pretty good answers
to those questions,
but I don't know, Oracle.
- There was a little awkward moment.
I don't know if you guys
heard it, natural body.
What's a function?
- Function.
(laughing)
- Oh dear.
- Well, making the interview a
little bit more interesting, right?
It doesn't have to be boring.
- Exactly.
But what is really interesting
is some of the language
he used to describe his educational
background and work experience.
So let's look at that now
in language takeaway.
- Language takeaway.
- Okay, so in language takeaway today,
we have seven words that we wanna focus on
before we give you some tips
about doing well on a job interview.
So let's take a look at the first word.
Course of study.
- Course of study.
- A course of study.
- So what is a course of study, exactly?
- Basically, it's like a plan
of study or a path of study.
- Okay, so his course of study
was business administration.
- Exactly, so that is his course of study.
Now let's take a look at our second word.
Track, track, track, track.
So he said he wanted
to gain some practical,
marketable skills that the information
management track provided.
- Exactly.
- So what does he mean by this track?
- Again, basically the track of study
is like the path of study.
- Okay.
So the direction of your study.
- Okay, so I guess it would be like, think
of a train and the train tracks, right?
- Exactly.
- Where the train travels.
So that's where it's taking you.
That's the path that he followed or
you should follow or you want to follow.
- Yes.
- Okay, that's pretty interesting.
- Mm-hmm.
- Now let's take a look at our third
word and it's a really nice conjunction.
Hence.
- Hence.
- H-E-N-C-E, hence.
Hence.
- So it sounds fancy, but
yes, what does it mean?
- What does it mean? - So, therefore.
- Yeah. - Right.
So you can use it as a
conjunction between two ideas.
So he said, what would be an
example of how you could use hints?
- You could say the economy is doing
poorly, hence people are losing their jobs.
- Okay.
Hence, so therefore inconsequence.
- Right.
- So exactly.
- But it just sounds a
lot more like professional.
- Informal.
- Formal. - Yeah.
- Okay, so try and use
this conjunction hints, right?
Instead of saying so, therefore.
- Yep, use it.
Okay, our fourth word.
- Pursued.
- He pursued a master's.
- Okay, so to pursue.
- To chase after something.
- To chase after.
- So you can pursue a
master's degree like he did.
- Yes, you can pursue a promotion.
- A dream.
- Nice one.
- Can you pursue a girl?
- Yes, you can.
- All right, so pursuit to chase.
- Yes.
- Okay.
Now let's look at our next word, strive.
Another great word you can use
in talking about your experience.
To strive is to try really hard.
- To try really hard.
- Yeah.
- Okay, so I know we have
some examples for strive.
- Yeah, let's take a listen.
- Example one.
- At our company, we are always
striving to improve our services.
- Example two.
- He really strived to get a
new job and his work paid off.
- Okay, great examples of
strive to fight, to try really hard.
- Yep.
- All right.
Okay, now the next word, I
didn't really know what it meant.
So this is really interesting.
Bread.
- Bread.
- So it's kind of like saying
bread, but adding a TH at the end.
- Yeah.
- Bread.
- Bread of experience.
- Okay, so this basically means it's wide.
- Exactly, so when you
have a great bread of
experience, you have a
wide variety of experience.
- Okay, so maybe in different
fields or in different jobs.
So you can have
experience like in marketing
and in a little bit in finance
and a little bit in management.
- Yes, a breadth of experience.
- All right.
All right, and now for the last
word, it's actually three in one.
- A three in one deal.
That actually they are very related.
Okay, right.
So when he talked
about his work experience,
he was saying he supervised and
coordinated the customer support team.
- Okay, so he watched over, right?
And made things work together well.
- Coordinate.
- Yes.
- So these are really great
verbs that you can use
when you're talking about
your job responsibilities.
I supervised, I coordinated.
And he was another really
great one is said to implement.
- To implement, to make
something happen, to put it in place.
- Right, so he implemented new strategies.
- Implemented new policies.
- Okay, to set in action.
- Exactly.
- All right.
So a lot of great vocabulary,
a lot of great stuff.
And well, you can use it for
when you are at a job interview.
So let's listen to this dialogue again.
And when we come back,
we're gonna give you some tips
so you'll do well in this
part of the job interview.
(upbeat music)
- Thanks for coming in today.
Did you have any trouble finding us?
Please, take a seat.
- Thank you.
So let's get started.
Tell me a bit about your
educational background.
- Sure, well, I graduated
with honors from Chesterson
University with a major
in business administration
with a specialization in information
management and I'm honored in psychology.
I chose this course of
study for two reasons.
I wanted to gain some practical, marketable
skills, which the information management
track provided, and I also
feel that the interpersonal skills
are essential for professional
success hence the minor in psychology.
- Interesting.
And your postgraduate studies?
- Well, I am really passionate
about consumer behavior.
So I pursued a master's in that area.
I also strive to keep my
professional skills current.
So I continuously attend seminars
and conferences related to
management and customer service.
(whooshing)
(clears throat) Very good.
Now, tell me a little bit
about your work experience.
I see here that you
previously worked at Oracle.
- Yeah, I worked as their
customer support manager,
which brought me a breadth of experience
in both client care and process management.
I supervised and coordinated
the customer support team
as well as implemented new strategies
to achieve better customer satisfaction.
(whooshing)
- Interesting.
- Yes, in this position, I was
able to make some pretty
significant contributions to the
overall success of the company.
With the different initiatives
that we implemented,
we lowered our turn rate to about 5%,
which had a direct impact on revenue.
(upbeat music)
- All right, well, I wanna
talk about two main things.
And the first thing I
wanna talk about is how you
address this question about
your educational background.
Like, what is the interviewer
looking to find out?
- Okay, perfect.
So when you are talking about
your educational background,
you shouldn't only talk about
your college degree, right?
- Yep.
- You should also talk about any
type of training that you've had.
- Yeah, I think it's really important
to let the interviewer know
that you're continually trying to update
your skills and improve your knowledge.
So any sort of courses
or seminars that you might
attend, this is a great
chance to highlight those.
- And that's what the
interview is looking for, right?
- Also, any trade publications, any
magazines that you read related to your job
is a great way to sort of highlight
your desire to keep learning?
- Well, I think that's really important
because it's good that
you went to a good
university, you got
disagreeing and everything,
but continuously training yourself and
maybe just by listening to business podcasts
or reading specific
magazines or stuff like that,
that is demonstrating that
you care about what you do
and that you are
continuously learning, right?
- Exactly.
- Okay, so those are the main things to
talk about in your educational background.
Now when this work experience question
pops up, what should you really say?
- When you're answering this question,
I think there's something
really important to keep in mind.
- What's that?
- You wanna make sure that you're
being as specific as possible, right?
- Right, so giving examples
of what you've done.
- Like really specifically what you did,
all of the sort of the main
achievements you have.
- Okay, so like for example,
we saw in our dialogue
that he talked about specific strategies
that he implemented to improve
customer support in that company.
- Right, and then he gave some numbers.
- Right, he said, yeah, he lowered
the churn rate to about 5%.
- So it's so important whenever you can
attach a number to
your success or your
achievement to be able
to do that in the interview.
Really, really demonstrates
your achievement.
- Yeah, I think that's really important.
And another thing when
you're talking about previous
jobs is make sure you
keep it on a positive.
- Yeah, yeah.
- Even if your experience was not very good
or you didn't like the
company or you had problems,
you should avoid talking about that
and always keep it on a positive note.
- Right, so if the interviewer asks
you why you wanna join this company,
why you're looking to
leave your current job,
you wanna give these positive reasons.
- Right, you don't wanna say, well,
because my boss was a jerk
or I didn't like the company
anymore, you know, you should answer
it with something positive like, well,
I think I need a change or
this job opportunity is more
aligned with what I wanna
do in the future, et cetera.
- Yeah, so positive
always on your interviews
and just again, prepare
for these questions
that are always gonna be there.
- So, Erica, I know that
you've done a lot of interviews
and I understand that you've
had a really weird question.
- Yes, in an interview, I
once got this question.
If you were a tree, what
kind of tree would you be?
- Really?
- Yeah, I'm not kidding, I
really was asked that question.
- What did you answer?
- I think I said that
I would wanna be a
willow tree because
they're really beautiful.
- Was that the right answer?
- I don't know, like what are you
supposed to answer to that question?
- I really don't know
what the right answer was.
- Well, some people,
yeah, they'll ask you just,
I don't know, random questions
to see what your response is.
I think also maybe it's just how you deal
with the pressure or with
the unexpected question.
- Right, so it's like, that
is pretty unexpected.
But I guess you handle it pretty well.
- Okay, well, I mean, I got the job, so--
- Ah, nice, all right.
- All right, I wanna
know from our listeners,
if they were a tree, what
kind of tree they would be.
- Yeah, and also tell us about, well,
your job experience or
your educational background.
Well, I know, for example, that I've
had a lot of different types of jobs.
I've even been that person that gets on
the bus and charges people the money.
- I know, like-- (laughing)
- You've had a good job under the sun.
- So, but it's great.
So tell us, what's the
weirdest job you've had?
What's the craziest or the
best job or any experiences?
- Yes, so visit our
website, EnglishPod.com.
Leave your questions and
comments there on the website.
- And we'll definitely be there to answer
them, and we hope to see you there.
- Thanks for listening, and goodbye.
(upbeat music)